Guide to the Lantern Slide Collection c. 1860-1942 PR 70
New-York Historical Society
Lantern Slide Collection
ca. 1860-1942
New-York Historical Society
PR 70
84.88 Linear feet (4,869 items)
The collection consists of 4,869 lantern slide photographs, most are 3 1/4 x 4 in. and were manufactured between 1860 and 1942. Many slides were connected with lecture presentations about New York and early American life sponsored by the New-York Historical Society. Some are also original photographs of views of Manhattan neighborhoods such as the Lower East Side, Greenwich Village, and Harlem as well as the borough of the Bronx. Images include bridges, rivers, transportation, churches, clubs, commercial and public buildings, monuments, parks, residences, schools, streets and theaters. Other interesting parts of the collection include a series on circus advertisements, several groups of cartoons and caricatures, and World War I American training camp slides. Some slides are copies of drawings that date back as far as the mid-17th century. Also in the collection are groups of slides manufactured outside the United States, including Germany, France, and Italy; most are tourist views. The Songs and Announcements sections of the collection contains slides used in theaters. The song slides were used to illustrate accompanying music and cover such genres as religious, popular, and patriotic music. The announcement slides provided reminders to viewers, such as removing their hats, or the slides advertised local businesses. Slides from amateur photographic clubs such as the American Slide Interchange, the Camera Club of New York, and the Society of Amateur Photographers of New York also account for a large portion of the collection.
Access Restrictions
Available by advance appointment only. To schedule an appointment, contact the Print Room Librarian at printroom@nyhistory.org. Photocopying undertaken by staff only. Limited to twenty exposures of stable, unbound material per day. (Researchers may not accrue unused copy amounts from previous days.)
Provenance
The collection's accession dates span from 1911 to 1955. See the Quarterly/Annual Reports in the Transparency File for descriptions of specific group accessions.
Scope and Contents Note
The Lantern Slides Collection contains 4,869 items, and makes up the bulk of the Transparency File (PR-70). The majority are 3 1/4 x 4 inch lantern slide photographs, many of which resulted from N-YHS' sponsorship, from 1900 to 1950, of numerous illustrated lectures about New York and early American life. Some of the slides in this collection are also original photographs of views of such Manhattan neighborhoods as the Lower East Side, Greenwich Village and Harlem. Well-represented photographers include Charles Simpson, Richard Hoe Lawrence and George E. Stonebridge. Among the dominant lantern slide manufacturers are the Charles Beseler Lantern Slide Co., Edward Van Altena, and T.H. McAllister-Keller and Co. Slides from amateur photographic clubs, such as the American Slide Interchange, the Camera club of New York, and the Society of Amateur Photographers of New York also account for a large portion of the collection.
The collection also contains a series of Circus advertisements, several groups of Cartoons and Caricatures, and a group of World War I American Training slides. Also included are groups of slides manufactured in countries outside of the United States, including Germany, France and Italy. Most of these are tourist views, but a few were produced by unidentified amateur photographers.
The majority of the images in the collection are relevant to New York City, and include bridges, rivers and transportation (including railroad material). Borough-specific New York City material includes subjects such as Churches, Clubs, Commercial Buildings, Monuments, Parks, Residences, Schools, Streets, and Theaters. As a whole, this portion of the collection provides a thorough look at the streets, culture and history of New York city throughout the late 1800s and early 1900s. Some of the slides are also copy work produced during that time of drawings that date as far back as the mid-17th century, functioning as examples of the sorts of images which 19th and 20th century slide makers and sponsors felt were worthy of preserving.
The Songs and Announcements sections of the collection contain slides which were used in the theaters. The announcements reminded viewers to take off their hats or go to a nearby ice cream shop after the show. The song slides were used to illustrate accompanying music, and cover such genres as religious, popular, and patriotic music.
Historical Note
Lantern slides are positive images on glass that were intended to be projected for viewing. In most cases, the emulsion is protected by a second piece of thin glass, and the unit is secured around all four edges with black paper tape. Many are individual, hand-painted works.
Lantern slides came into wide use in the United States after the 1860s. During the 1890s, magic lanterns were in high fashion as an extension of photography. Lantern slide shows, or the magic lantern, became popular home entertainment and served as an accompaniment to speakers on the lecture circuit. Lantern slides reached their popularity about 1900 and continued to be widely used until the 1930s, when they were gradually replaced by the more convenient 35-mm slides.
Organization of the Collection
This collection is organized into series:
Series I: General Lantern Slides
Series II: Songs
Series III: Announcements
Series IV: Special Formats
Theaters -- New York (State) -- New York.; New York (N.Y.) -- Buildings, structures, etc.; Drawings (visual works); Yorkville (New York, N.Y.); Dwellings -- New York (State) -- New York.; United States -- Social life and customs.; Transportation -- New York (State) -- New York.; Transparencies; Songs -- Texts.; School buildings -- New York (State) -- New York.; Rivers -- New York (State) -- New York.; Germany -- Description and travel.; France -- Description and travel.; Commercial buildings -- New York (State) -- New York.; Clubs -- New York (State) -- New York.; Church buildings -- New York (State) -- New York.; Chelsea (Manhattan, New York, N.Y.); Caricatures and cartoons.; Bronx (New York, N.Y.) -- Description and travel.; New York (N.Y.) -- Social life and customs.; Bridges -- New York (State) -- New York.; Announcements; Advertising -- Circus; Greenwich Village (New York, N.Y.); Harlem (New York, N.Y.); Italy -- Description and travel.; Lantern slides.; Lower East Side (New York, N.Y.); Military training camps -- United States.; Monuments -- New York (State) -- New York.; Streets -- New York (State) -- New York.; New York (N.Y.) -- Description and travel.; Parks -- New York (State) -- New York.; Public buildings -- New York (State) -- New York.; World War, 1914-1918 -- United States.; American Slide Interchange; Van Altena, Edward; T.H. McAllister-Keller Co.; Stonebridge, George E.; Society of Amateur Photographers of New York; Simpson, Charles; Lawrence, Richard Hoe; Dodd, George C.; Charles Beseler Co.; Camera Club of New York
- Series I: General Lantern Slides, 1
  - Copy Slides--"An Authentic Narrative…the Death of Major Andre…" by Joshua Hett Smith, Esq. (Box 1, Item PR-070-0001-0001)
    General note
    Copy slides of: "An Authentic Narrative of the Causes Which Led to the Death of Major Andre, Adjunct-General of His Majesty's Forces in North America" by Joshua Hett Smith, Esq. with a "Monody on the Death of Major Andre". Original text in NYHS Library
  - Copy Slides--Museums (Box 2, 3, Item PR-070-0001-0002)
    Reproductions of façade views and interiors of assorted American museums. See [Name] for list of museums and [Place] for list of locations.
  - Copy Slides--New York City Hotels (Box 4, 5, 6, 7, Item PR-070-0001-0003)
    Copy slides (along with some copy negatives) of drawings and photographs of New York City hotels.
  - Copy Slides--World News 1912-1913 (Box 8, 9, 10, Item PR-070-0001-0004)
    Clips of images with text concerning foreign and domestic news for the years 1912 to 1913, including topics such as the first World's Series, Panama Canal, Japanese migrant workers, New York Marathon, Salvation Army War Chariot, fashion, suffrage demonstr
  - Lectures--"Stereopticon Views of the Great Blizzard of 1888" by Mr. Washbourn, 1888, 1938 (Box 10, 11, Item PR-070-0001-0005)
    From Lecture Series by Mr. Washbourn: "Stereopticon Views of the Great Blizzard of 1888" for the 16th annual luncheon of the Blizzard Men of 1888. Images of Blizzard of 1888, including train wrecks, streets and buildings throughout NY, NJ, Mass. and Conn
  - Photographers, 1889 (Box 11, Item PR-070-0001-0006)
    Penn Station, Rural Activities, portraits, NYC views (near Harlem River), composite photos, Hudson River, Ft. Putnam, (New York, N.Y.) Central RR Fire, Society of Amateur Photographers of N.Y. meeting room, Statue of Liberty, Beggar in India, crowd at doc
  - Photographers--Burton, Thomas J., 1890 (Box 11, Item PR-070-0001-0007)
    Window on 10th St. near 5th Ave., Barry's at 8th Ave. and 152nd St., view of an unidentified house, and image of Battery Park.
  - Photographers--Foster, T. (Box 11, Item PR-070-0001-0008)
    Hand-tinted images of rural activities, mostly near train tracks, including view of children on toy horses, and men and women walking on or near railroad tracks.
  - Photographers--Hibbard, C.C. (Box 11, Item PR-070-0001-0009)
    Views of Columbus Arch, General Sherman's funeral, precession at Grant Monument, and Columbus Celebration on 5th Ave., as well as an image of a boat, a house, and some people in the water surrounded by ducks.
  - Photographers--Hull, Charles Wager (Box 12, Item PR-070-0001-0010)
    Images of sailboats steamboats at sail, both on Long Island Sound and near Coney Island.
  - Photographers--Langill & Bodfish (Box 12, Item PR-070-0001-0011)
    View of Harlem St. with trolleys and carriages, as well as pedestrians and elevated train tracks; Hand-tinted copy image of people in ocean, possibly Coney Island.
  - Photographers--Lawrence, Richard Hoe, 1888 (Box 12, Item PR-070-0001-0012)
    Views of Sawmill River, Westchester County, N.Y., as well as ice skating in Central Park, Trinity Church in snow, Broad St. Mills Building and Sub-Treasury, High Bridge, and an interior view of a 7th Regiment veteran's room.
  - Photographers--Morris, Charles F., c. 1953-1954 (Box 12, Item PR-070-0001-0013)
    Images of the Third Avenue El taken about 2-3 years before it was ripped down.
  - Photographers--Oppenheim, William George (Box 12, Item PR-070-0001-0014)
    There may be more of this photographers work at other locations in the collection. These images are mostly of N.Y. Scenes, including the Herald Office Buildings, St. Paul's Church, Coenties St., and Fulton St., as well as one image of Spuyten Duyvil.
  - Photographers--Rau, William H. (Box 12, Item PR-070-0001-0015)
    Penn Station images. There may be more images by this photographer in the rest of the collection.
  - Photographers--Schoen, A.P. (Box 12, Item PR-070-0001-0016)
    Central Park foot bridge in winter, and Sixth Ave. arboratorium.
  - Photographers--Simpson, Charles, 1896, 1888 (Box 13, 14, 15, Item PR-070-0001-0017)
    Blizzard of 1888, parades (including St. Patrick's Day), statues and monuments, New York street scenes (including Mott St.), parks, Upstate New York (including Niagara Falls during winter), St. Lawrence River, water views, foreign views (including Spain),
  - Photographers--Stonebridge (Box 15, 16, 17, 18, 19, Item PR-070-0001-0018)
    Series: Rural Activities; Series: Spanish-American War.
  - Photographers--Tiemann, H.N. (Box 19, Item PR-070-0001-0019)
    7th Regiment Monument in Central Park; Children in ocean surf.
  - Photographers--Uhle, John Bethell (Box 19, Item PR-070-0001-0020)
    Revolutionary Monument in Sleepy Hollow Cemetery; Junction of new and old roads in Fox Meadows.
  - Photographers--Van Altena, Edward (Box 19, Item PR-070-0001-0021)
    Beach views with children and swimmers; View of young girl with large dog--all hand-tinted.
  - Photographers--Warrin, Ernest (Box 19, Item PR-070-0001-0022)
    These images are probably part of a Society of Amateur Photographers of N.Y. series. They include a portrait, an ocean view of Hogg Island, three Jamaican boys, and an image of men on a barge full of garbage.
  - Portraits--Group (Box 19, Item PR-070-0001-0023)
    President Harding and Cabinet; Mr. & Mrs. Barek, Mr. & Mrs. Dunnmore, Mr. & Mrs. Wall, Wall Jr. by W.L. Calver; collage of presidential portraits?; Asian theater troupe; baseball team portrait; several group portraits of Church choirs; elementary school p
  - Portraits--Individual, 1881, 1814 (Box 20, Item PR-070-0001-0024)
    Assorted unidentified/unlabeled portraits, as well as portrait of the Last Slave on Staten Island (Perrine, Ben), Nellie Bly, George Dewey, Herbert Hoover, William McKinley, Elisha Morgan, John Pershing, Edgar Allen Poe, and Anna and Susan Bartlett; port
  - Series--American Colonial Life (Box 20, Item PR-070-0001-0025)
    Images representing Colonial life, including costumes, using tools, and candle making.
  - Series--Architectural Photographs (Box 21, 22, 23, 24, Item PR-070-0001-0026)
    Series of document photographs of work of assorted architects, including interiors, exteriors and architectural renderings and plans--originally labeled "Mr. Andrews' Slides." Some of the architects include the following: Davis, Alexander Jackson, 1803
  - Series--Audubon and New York Views (Box 24, Item PR-070-0001-0027)
    Audubon nature images, as well as assorted non-Audubon landscapes, including Spuyten Duyvil, Bronx Valley Tuckahoe and others. Also, this series contains some images of schoolchildren. These slides are still contained in their original box, which also h
  - Series--Blizzard of 1888 (Box 25, Item PR-070-0001-0028)
    Images of New York City's Blizzard of 1888, including: shoveling snow at Broadway near Trinity Church; Hotel Martin at University and 9th St.; West 11th St. b/t West and Washington Sts. Snow banks and street lamps; Bway at 10th St. trees and bakery with c
  - Series--Circuses & shows (Box 25, 26, Item PR-070-0001-0029)
    Mainly copy work, possibly for a lecture on circuses and shows. These slides include reproductions of circus posters and show advertisements, including some in color, as well as advertisements for specific attractions (human curiosities, as well as anima
  - Series--Europe (Box 27, Item PR-070-0001-0030)
    Unlabeled images from one box of European looking cities (possibly near the Rhine, Italy, France?). Includes mountain and monument views, as well as scenes with children, marketplaces and railroads.
  - Series--Farm Life (Box 27, 28, Item PR-070-0001-0031)
    Images of Farm Life, such as milking cows, binding grain, planting corn, woodpecker's nest, chicks drinking, clump of iris, raking hay, etc.
  - Series--Gilbert's Elevated Railroad and Pneumatic Dispatch (Box 28, Item PR-070-0001-0032)
    Copy slides of drawings depicting design and structure of Dr. R. H. Gilbert's Elevated Railroad and Pneumatic Dispatch, as well as pertinent news clippings.
  - Series--Lake George Resort Life (Box 28, 29, Item PR-070-0001-0033)
    Mostly nature views of Lake George, as well as some images of resort residents canoeing, swimming, rock climbing, etc.
  - Series--New York City Views, 1873, 1886, 1833 (Box 29, 30, Item PR-070-0001-0034)
    Assorted New York City view of stores, snow, churches, portraits, houses, trains, bridges, waterfronts and accidents. Mostly unlabeled. Among the labeled are views of the Macomb's Dam Bridge, a Congregational Church on 125th St. and 2nd Ave., Joseph Bro
  - Series--Portraits (Box 30, Item PR-070-0001-0035)
    Individual Portraits of men with poetic titles.
  - Series--Society of Amateur Photographers of N.Y.? (Box 30, 31, Item PR-070-0001-0036)
    Images were originally boxed with labeled Society of Amateur Photographers of N.Y. work, and mats bear some resemblance, so these unlabeled slides have been grouped together here.
  - Series--Upstate New York (Box 31, 32, 33, 34, Item PR-070-0001-0037)
    Assorted views, mostly with accompanying titles, possibly for a lecture or else by one single unidentified photographer. Includes a large amount of upstate New York views, including Albany (Boy's Academy, Business College), Saratoga, Hotel Champlain, Bru
  - Subjects--American Revolution, 1917, 1913, 1915, 1934 (Box 34, Item PR-070-0001-0038)
    Images of American Revolutionary sites, including excavation.
  - Subjects--Archaeology (Box 34, Item PR-070-0001-0039)
    Unlabeled images of men and women involved in archaeological work.
  - Subjects--Cartoons (Commentary) (Box 34, 35, Item PR-070-0001-0040)
    Photographing the Baby series; Silhouette series; other individual slides, including caricatures and social commentary.
  - Subjects--Cartoons (Commentary)--Ethnic stereotypes (Box 35, Item PR-070-0001-0041)
    Images and caricatures which include stereotypes Afro-Americans.
  - Subjects--Cartoons (Commentary)--Political Cartoons (Box 35, Item PR-070-0001-0042)
    Cartoons portraying political issues, inlcuding an image of Uncle Sam with Spanish-American War relevance.
  - Subjects--Executions (Law) (Box 35, Item PR-070-0001-0043)
    Unidentified image of a hanging.
  - Subjects--Fashion, 1910 (Box 35, 36, Item PR-070-0001-0044)
    Mostly copy work--images of women modeling early 1900 clothing and accessories.
  - Subjects--Fire fighters (Box 36, Item PR-070-0001-0045)
    Group portrait at Firefighter's Monument; Views of fire fighters following the Equitable Fire; Bronx fire fighting companies; Fire Engine.
  - Subjects--Indians of North America (Box 36, Item PR-070-0001-0046)
    Images include Indian skeletons, basket weavers, Guides and Chiefs.
  - Subjects--Military, 1890, 1935 (Box 36, Item PR-070-0001-0047)
    Assorted views of Washington Heights, Watkins Glen sentry bridge, West Point, Peekskill, including parades, monuments, horses, officers, etc.
  - Subjects--Parades and Processions, 1916, 1917, 1918, 1930, 1920, 1899, 1914 (Box 36, 37, Item PR-070-0001-0048)
    Flag Day--Sons of Revolution--view of officials with band standing in background; two unidentified view of parade and dedication ceremony, showing marching band and crowds of people with umbrellas; Other assorted parades and processions include: Preparedn
  - Subjects--Rivers (Box 37, Item PR-070-0001-0049)
    Unidentified images of rivers, one includes a dam and factory.
  - Subjects--Ships, 1904 (Box 37, Item PR-070-0001-0050)
    Images of unidentified yachts, warships, and dhows; Images of assorted ships, including the Storm King, Periwinkle (in Forest Grove), Laza (Palisades), and several ships involved in accidents; Capt. Sygsbee and Con. Gen. Lee in rowboat with flag and sever
  - Subjects--Ships--Ocean Liners, 1920's (Box 37, 38, Item PR-070-0001-0051)
    Images of Ocean Liners, including decks, passengers, celebrations, shuffleboard and the like.
  - Subjects--Ships--Steamboats, 1939 (Box 38, Item PR-070-0001-0052)
    Images of steamers, including the Robert Fulton, Mary Powell, Connecticut, Harlem, and the Narrangansett.
  - Subjects--Spanish-American War (Box 38, Item PR-070-0001-0053)
    Image of Santa Clara, Cuba street barricade, as well as a destroyer, and Admiral Dewey portrait.
  - Subjects--Transportation (Box 38, Item PR-070-0001-0054)
    Bicyclists in unidentified Park (possibly Central?); 6 horse wagon in park; Woman in Rickshaw; Woman driving buggy through park; Family standing near and sitting inside car; Man driving 2-horse carriage; small boys with donkey-driven cart; Military? Offic
  - Subjects--Transportation--Railroads (Box 38, Item PR-070-0001-0055)
    Unidentified views of trains and railroad stations/depots, including an interior of a waiting room; unidentified view of train tracks passing through residential area; unidentified view of hanging railroad bridge.
  - Subjects--Views (Box 38, Item PR-070-0001-0056)
    Views of ponds, scenery, ocean, trees, etc.; one view could possibly be naval-related, but it is unlabeled.
  - Subjects--World War I--American Training Camps (Box 38, 39, Item PR-070-0001-0057)
    Views include: Winter Pup Tents, trenches, training towns, targets, supply trains, shooting galleries, Red Cross, recruits, marching, field pieces, cavalry training, and barracks,
  - Subjects--World War I--Ships (Box 39, 40, Item PR-070-0001-0058)
    WWI Naval Training Ships, battleships firing, smoke screens, battleships, British Cruisers, USS Oregon, USS Pennsylvania, The Chicago, and the Olympic.
  - Subjects--World War II, 1944, 1942, 1941 (Box 40, Item PR-070-0001-0059)
    Images from Battle of Midway, Doolittle's Raid, Normandy and Pearl Harbor.
  - Unidentified--Buildings (Box 40, Item PR-070-0001-0060)
    Views of unidentified buildings, one could possible be a fort, and the others are most likely commercial or government property.
  - Unidentified--Engraving Reproductions (Box 40, Item PR-070-0001-0061)
    Reproductions of engravings of genre scenes and instructional images; some of these images seem as if they might go together.
  - Unidentified--Residences (Box 40, 41, Item PR-070-0001-0062)
    Images of facades and interiors of unidentified houses and home, most probably all in New York--some of these views include people and interiors, as well as grounds; Mailman with dog on fence in front of unidentified house; Men harvesting corn on farmland
  - Unidentified--Streets (Box 41, Item PR-070-0001-0063)
    Unidentified street images, some include people.
  - Asia-Japan (Box 41, Item PR-070-0001-0064)
    Image of cherry trees blossoming in Ueno Park, Tokyo.
  - Europe (Box 41, Item PR-070-0001-0065)
    Views of unidentified European cities.
  - Europe-France (Box 41, Item PR-070-0001-0066)
    Assorted (mostly tourist) images of France, especially Paris, including tree-lined streets, Arc de Triumph, the Opera house, Notre Dame, Eiffel Tower, and a bridge with St. Peter and the Louvre, as well as some unidentified views.
  - Europe-Germany (Box 41, Item PR-070-0001-0067)
    Success Lake, Hamburg Free Dock and Harbor, Falls of the Rhine, rivers and houses.
  - Europe-Italy (Box 41, Item PR-070-0001-0068)
    Assorted (mostly tourist) images of Italy, especially Rome--views of the Vatican Library, Coliseum, Borghese Gardens; aerial views and landmark images.
  - Europe-Russia (Box 42, Item PR-070-0001-0069)
    Peasants posed in front of small home.
  - Europe-Spain-Seville (Box 42, Item PR-070-0001-0070)
    Images of an unidentified park in Seville.
  - Arizona (Box 42, Item PR-070-0001-0071)
    Williams Canyon Narrows with donkey--Grand Canyon.
  - California, 1856 (Box 42, Item PR-070-0001-0072)
    Mission San Gabriel Arcangel; San Diego Mission; old mill and water wheel in Calistoga; Big trees, horse carriage and cabin; Merced River, Yosemite; Fort Vigilance, S.F.; Tents of Refugees in S.F.; view of large trees, cabin, and 4 horse carriage; Image o
  - Colorado (Box 42, Item PR-070-0001-0073)
    Colorado Springs, Ute Indians
  - District of Columbia-Washington (Box 42, Item PR-070-0001-0074)
    Penn. Ave.; Library of Congress; Capitol; Capitol viewed from Congressional Library; Supreme Court chamber; house where Lincoln died; carriage bus from East Capitol Street to 15th & Boundary.
  - Maryland, 1914 (Box 42, Item PR-070-0001-0075)
    All Hallows Parish Church; Trinity Church, Dorchester Parish; Old Council House, Annapolis; Tablet on Annapolis Tulip.
  - Massachusetts (Box 42, Item PR-070-0001-0076)